[{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following will cause a decrease in market equlibrium price and an increase in market equilibrium quantity<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An increase in supply","An increase in demand","A decease in demand","A decrease in supply"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A consumer has <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>100 of income to spend on goods X and Y. The price of good X is <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>10, and the price of good Y is <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>2. Which of the following combinations of X and Y is not affordable?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10X and 0Y","6X and 25Y","4Y and 20Y","5Y and 25Y"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>As a percentage of labour force, the unemployment rate measures:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The number of people in an economy who do not have jobs","The number of people in an economy who have jobs","The number of people who are out of work and actively looking for work","The number of people who are looking for work."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A budget constraint describes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A person's production possibilities","A person's production opportunities","The shape of the person demand curve","The limits to a person's consumption possibilities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marginal utility is the <\/strong><\/p>","options":["Pleasure or satisfaction from consuming a particular quantity of a good","Average utility per unit consumed","Change in total utility that results from a one unit change in the quantity of a good consumed","Quantity of goods that a consumer prefers"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A rational consumer, does not:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Think marginally","Intentionally make himself or herself worse off","Try to maximize net benefit from consulting goods services","Ever consume the wrong amount"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following determines price in a capitalist economy ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Government","Invisible","Producer","Consumer"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which approach do economists use to compute national output by adding up all the final goods and revenues produced in a country during a year calculated as a market price<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Value Added Approach","Expenditure Approach","Product Approach","National Savings"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Equilibrium in the financial market requires that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Money supply equals money demand","Money supply equals reserves demand","Checkable deposits equal overall supply of money","Money supply equals overall demand for money"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statement is true of a monopoly markets ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Barrier to entry exist in the short run, but not in the long run","Price is greater than marginal revenue but less than margin cost","Demand is more elastic than the demand for a perfectly competitive firms output","Demand for the Firm's product is also the market demand for the product."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these will not be a typical consequence of an import tariff<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Producer surplus increases in the domestic market","Consumer surplus increases in the domestic market","Deadweight loss is created","Government revenue is created"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The participation rate is the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ratio of those working to those looking for work","Ratio of the unemployed to the labour force to the population","Ratio of the labour force to the population","Ratio of the employed to the labour force"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Microeconomics is concerned with?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The aggregate or total levels of income, employment and output","A detailed examination of specific economic units that make up the economic system","Positive economics, but not normative economics","The establishing of an overall view of the operation of the economic system"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the short run, firms increase output by:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increasing the amount of labour used","Decreasing the size of their plant","Increasing the site of their plant","Decreasing the amount of labour used"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When excess production results in loss leading to retrenchment of workers in a particular firm. we have unemployment<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Structural","Residual","Voluntary","Cyclical"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>__________ is a market for the sale and purchase of existing securities<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Primary markets","Secondary market","Secondary market","Capital market"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand curve for a commodity is more elastic when?<br><\/strong><\/p>","options":["The greater the number of good substitutes available","The greater the proportion of income spent on the commodity","The longer the period of time considered","All of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the real market prices of a product is <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>20 per unit and in this market, the government places a price ceiling at <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>30 per unit, what will happen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["People will buy the product at N30","There will be surplus of the product in the market","Government price ceiling will not be effective","Government can put price ceiling below or above equilibrium price"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A pricing behaviour in which a firm charges different prices to different consumers for the same good or service is known as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Uniform pricing behaviour","Price discrimination","Market separability","Price differentiation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In computation of GDP, the following are not included except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All final goods and produced and sold within the country","All used goods or goods sold outside of traditional market","All produce from home gardens that is grown consumed by household","All the farm products that farmers exchange among themselves without ever being sold"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The short-run equilibrium for a monopolist is achieved when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price equals MC","Price equals MR","MR equal MC","MR equal AR"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following leads to an initial increase in the aggregate demand of an economy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An increase in the price of energy","A decrease in consumer wealth","An increase in investment","An increase in the wage rate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A utility function is homothetic if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The marginal utility depends on the average of the goods","The total utility depends on the sum of the goods","The marginal rate of substitution for the function depends only on the ratio of the amount of the two good","The MRS for the function depends on the total quantities of the two goods"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If an oligopolist incurs losses in the short run, then in the long run.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It will stay in business","It will go out of business.","It will break even","It will merge with other firms"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm maximizes its total profits when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total revenue equals total cost.","Total cost exceeds total revenue by the greatest amount","Total revenue exceeds total cost by the greatest amount","It is at the breakeven point"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Perfect price elastic supply means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["No change in supply as price changes","Any change in price completely stops suply","Changes in price double supply","A change in price leads to proportionate change in supply"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>When disequilibrium between supply and demand has tendencies to be restored to another equilibrium point over a definite path of a time frame, the equilibrium is regarded as;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dynamic and convergence equilibrium","State and Convergence equilibrium","Static and Divergence equilibrium","Dynamic and Divergence equilibrium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>A demand curve facing the pure monopolist is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfectly price elastic","Perfectly price inelastic","Negatively sloped","Positively sloped"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Consumers are referred to as 'the king' in which of these economic systems ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Planned economy","Mixed economy","Socialist economy","Free market economy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The real cost of a commodity is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The cost of the alternative that has to be sacrificed for it","Opportunity of buying the commodity is mixed","Its market price","The alternative  that  has  to be forgone in order to purchase it."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The law of diminishing returns begins to operate when teh&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total product begins to rise","Total product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to rise","Marginal product begins to fall"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic problems arise mainly as a result of?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inaccurate statistical data","Excessive wastage of available resources","Lack of foresight on the part of resource users","Limitations in available  resources."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three (3) major agents of an economic system are the:&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumers, workers and producers","Individuals, firms and  government","Politicians, bankers and entrepreneur","Consumers, producers and government"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the government chooses to use resources to build a school, these resources are no longer available to build a highway. This&nbsp; choice illustrates the concept of:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["market mechanism","opportunity cost","trade by barter","macroeconomics"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following can lead&nbsp; to change in supply, except;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Change in weather","Change in the price of the product","Change in the price of related products","Change in attitude of producers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Zero price elastic demand of a commodity means that?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The product has no value when it comes to price evaluation","The product is a public goods, thus no price is to be paid to consume it","The quantity purchased of the product remains the same at all price level","The quantity purchased of the product can be changed to any level without any change in price"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>A of the following are true about Total Product, Marginal product and Average product except one:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["When TP is at the maximum, MP equals zero","AP equals MP when MP is at the Maximum","When TP is falling, MP is negative","When TP is at the maximum, AP is positive"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average cost is equal to Marginal cost when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average cost is at the maximum","Average cost is at the minimum","Marginal cost is at the minimum","Marginal cost is at the maximum"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The best measure of economic well-being in any economy is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["GDP per capital","GOP","GNP","National Income"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm that is running at a loss will continue to produce in the short-run if its:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["P> AVC","P=AVC","P<AVC","P=AVC"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is not true: In the long-run,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost equals variable cost","Average cost equals average variable cost","Average fixed cost equals zero","Average cost is the addition of average fixed cost and Average variable cost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>GOP per capital is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["GOP\/labour force","GDP\/population","GDP\/unemployed","GOP\/working population"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>All these are example of biases in using GDP or GNP to measure economic well-being except:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Population growth","Price changes","Non-market-activities","Market activities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>All these are example of biases in using GDP or GNP to measure economic well-being except:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Population growth","Price changes","Non-market-activities","Market activities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between economic growth and economic development is that the latter deals with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["economic growth and structural change","economic growth and output change","economic growth and GOP change","economic growth and income change"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Suppose the consumer price index (CPI) in 1989 is&nbsp; 124.0 and the CPI in 1990 is 130.7 the CPI expressed as a percentage is&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["6.7%","5.4%","7.6%","4.5%"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the short run horizon of production,&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All inputs can be varied","One input is varied","All inputs are fixed","One input, at least, is varied"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a limited relevance of commodity money:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Costliness of transaction","It limits market size","It happens specialization","It is held as a store of wealth"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the shortrun, all of the following&nbsp; are applicable&nbsp; except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Output may be increased by changing all factors by the same proportion","Diminishing returns","There are sunk costs","The total cost curve is the same as the total variable cost curve"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The sum of&nbsp; MPS and MPC is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Greater than 1 but less than infinity","Greater than 0 but less than 1","Equal to 1","None of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>For a perfectly competitive market, the shape of&nbsp; the ________&nbsp; is horizontal while the ___________ is downward slopping.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Industry's demand curve\/industry's supply curve","Firm's supply curve\/industry's supply curve","Firm's demand curve\/industry's demand curve\/industry's demand curve","Industry's demand curve\/firm's demand curve"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Demand for money is a?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Composite demand","Derived demand","Joint demand","B and C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cross elasticity of demand between X and Y is zero, then&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["X and Y are substitutes","X and Y are complements","X and Y are dependent on each other","X and Y are independent of  each other"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following correctly defines inflation ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A one - time increase in commodity prices","A period when prices increase rapidly","A sustained increase in the overall price level","An increase in the overall level of business activity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a market for good X is&nbsp; in disequilibrium, which of the following statements is true about the quantity of X that is actually exchanged ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is determined by the forces of demand","It is determined  by the forces of supply","It is determined by both demand and supply forces","It is  determined by the forces of demand or supply, whichever is shorter"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>How can we eliminate a surplus in a commodity market ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase quantity supplied","Decrease quantity demanded","Allowing price to fall towards equilibrium","Allowing price to rise towards equilibrium"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Identify one among the following which is NOT part of the objectives or functions of the African Development Bank (ADB)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Provision of technical assistance for development projects","Provision of funds for the supply and demand of infrastructural facilities","Adoption of a common tariff policy for trade and development","Provision of fund for agricultural development"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the product of any firm in an industry is not perceived by consumers as a perfect substitute for the product of any other firm in the same industry, we have&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfect competition","Monopoly","Oligopolist","Monopolistic competition"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of the following situations do we have a free good ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["At zero price, more is demanded than supplied","At zero price, quantity supplied exceeds quantity demanded","At equilibrium price, quantity supply is  equal to quantity demanded","Any quantity can be obtained when the price is  low"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics, a commodity is said to have an opportunity cost because?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The price of the commodity is high","The commodity is  scarce","Another good may have been purchased instead of it.","The commodity provides many benefits"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following options is not correct<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Any point inside the product possibility curve indicates unemployment or underemployment","Increase in the price of a commodity leads to a fall in the demand for its substitute","The fixing of price above the equilibrium price levels leads to surplus of the commodity","An increase in both market supply and  market demand may not result in a change in equilibrium price and quantity."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country's&nbsp; aggregate consumption was <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>20 million. Following an increase in GDP to J4120 million, consumption increased to <span style=\"text-decoration: line-through;\">N<\/span>25 million. The marginal propensity to consume is given as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.25","0.50","0.75","0.80"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a measure for controlling inflation by the Central Bank ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Open market operation","Reserve requirements","Sale of treasury bills","Change of Central Bank Governor"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A 50% increase in the quantity demanded of a commodity, following a 100% decrease in its price, shows that the commodity has<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fairly elastic demand","Unitary elastic demand","Inelastic demand","Perfectly elastic demand"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>As total utility is increasing, marginal utility is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Negative and decreasing","Positive and increasing","Positive and decreasing","Zero"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is true ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Disposal income is the only variable that determines consumption","Investment spending is positively related to the rate of interest","Imports lead to a decrease in the level of exports","Imports lead to a decrease in spending on locally produced goods and services"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following will benefit a producer who wants to maximize profit ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reduce price when demand is inelestic","Increase price when demand is inelastic","Reduce price when demand is elastic","Fixed the price of his commodity based on the price of other producers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Based on the fact that demand curve shows the maximum price at which consumers will buy, it then shows<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average benefit","Marginal benefit","Total benefit","Optimal satisfaction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money that a government has required to be accepted in settlement of debts is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Commodity money","Currency value","Barter","Legal tender"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is one of the responsibilities of the Central Bank of Nigeria ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Issuing new bond to finance public sector borrowing requirements","Auditing the various agencies and departments of government","Loaning money to other countries that transact business with Nigeria","Assisting banks that are in financial position"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The law of comparative cost and absolute cost advantage are not same in that;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The former requires that one of the countries has absolute advantage in the two goods but the latter does not","The former requires one country to have at least absolute advantage in one of the trading goods over the other country but the latter does not","The former does not require any of the two goods but the latter requires that one of the countries should have absolute advantage in any of all the goods.","Former does not require any of the country to have absolute advantage in any of the two goods but latter require that one of the countries should have absolute advantage in at least one of  t"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>When demand for a product is price inelastic, which of the following can happen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumers suffer the entire increase in tax on the product","Product suffers the entire increase in tax on the product","Producer suffers larger proportion of  the increase in tax on the product.","Consumers suffer larger proportion of the increase in tax on the product."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Disposable income means;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income that is lost after tax has been removed","Income that could be spend when tax has been removed","Income that tax authority mandated to be given to charity when tax has been removed","Income to be disposed secretly for future spending after tax has been removed."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Price discrimination exist when&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The same product in the same quality is sold for different prices of the same buyer","The same product of the same quality is sold for different prices to different buyers","Different products are sold for the same price to the same buyers","Different products are sold for the same price for to different buyers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A commodity is said to be price inelastic if?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Changes in the quantity purchased of a good is less than proportionate to changes in its price","Changes in the quantity purchased of a good is proportionate to changes in its  price","Changes in the quantity purchased of a good is more than proportionate to changes in its price","The quantity purchased of a good never responds to change in its price"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The parameter 'y' in a consumption function of the form; c= a+by; where Y is the National income is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal benefit of consumption","Marginal propensity to purchase","Marginal propensity to consume","Marginal propensity to save"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Indifference curve and isoquant are respectively relevant in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Theories of consumer behaviours and production","Theories of human indifference and production","Theories of trade and production","Theories of production and trade"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Perfect price elastic supply means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["No change in supply as price changes","Any change in price completely stops supply","Changes in price doubles supply","A change in price leads to proportionate change in supply."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Change in demand and change in quantity demanded are not the same because?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All factors affecting change in demand also affects change in quantity demanded except income","All factors affecting change in demand are not affecting change in quantity demanded except income","Many factors leads to change in demand but only change in price affects change in quantity demanded","Many factors leads to change in demand but only change in income affects change in quantity demanded"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following is the&nbsp; main differnce between firm and industry<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Industry is the group of firms producing  related products","Industry is the group of firms in the manufacturing  sector","Industry is the group of  firms in different sectors of the economy","Industry is the group of firms with a single pressure group"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Roles of the central bank include all of the following except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Lender of last resort to commercial bank","Banker to commercial bank","Regulator of both the money and capital markets","Receipt of government deposits"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Ordinary shareholders and preferential shareholders are different because:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Preferential shareholders participate and can vote and be voted for during  the AGM","Ordinary shareholders are given priority in case the company is liquidated","Preferential shareholders are prominent shareholders than ordinary shareholders","Ordinary shareholders are the core shareholders in the company"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Yam and palm oil are used together; therefore&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Yam is a substitute good while  palm oil is a complimentary good","Yam is complimentary good while palm oil is a substitute good","Yam and palm oil are complementary goods","Yam and beans are substitute goods"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Private and public limited liability companies are not the same because&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Former is limited is to fifty shareholders but not the latter","Both are not legal entities","Former is established secretly but  latter is located  in central places","Former is  managed by board of directors but latter is managed by board of management"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the salary of a worker increases from 60,000 Naira to 80,000 Naira and the average price of certain commodities consumed by the worker increases from 120 Naira to 160 Naira then?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The nominal income increases but the real income remains constant","The real income increases, but nominal income has reduced","The nominal income increases, but real income decreases","Both the nominal and real income increases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Discount rate means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rate at which money are borrowed from commercial bank","Rate at which bank receive deposit from the public","Central  banker rate on the money borrowed by commercial banks","Commercial bank rate on the money borrowed from other commercial banks"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the government expenditure and income are the same in a fiscal year, this is referred&nbsp; as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Net balance","Zero balanced budget","Balanced budget","Net income"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Inflation as a result of increase in payment for factors of production is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cost-pull inflation","Demand-push inflation","Cost-push inflation","Demand pull-inflation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>When Lump-sum tax is paid by a producer, it means that;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The tax is paid proportional to the quantity of output produced","The tax is paid regardless of volume of output","The tax is paid in arrears","The tax is returned to the producer after the payment"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following is not correct <\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average variable cost equals average total cost minus average fixed cost","Average fixed cost equals average variable  cost minus average total cost","Average total cost equals averages variables cost plus average fixed cost","Average total cost minus average variable cost equals average fixed cost"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Normal profit means;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["All the accountant cost are covered but not all the economist cost","All the economist cost are covered but not all the accountant cost","More than economist cost are covered","None of the economist and accountant costs is covered"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the price of commodity X increases because of the increase in the price vis-a-vis the increase in demand for another commodity Y, the two commodities are likely to be?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Complimentary","Substitute","Composite","Intermediate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following may not inflate the National Income figure<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Students bursary","Owners occupied houses","Office inducement","Intermediate goods"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Legal Entity means&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A company is owned by large number of people","A company is  owned by small number of people","A company is insulated  against litigation","A company is not  insulated against litigation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>In&nbsp; the ownership structure of a joint-stock company, the following is correct;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ordinary shareholders are stronger than preferential shareholders","Preferential shareholders are stronger than ordinary shareholders","Ordinary shareholders are settled first in case of company's liquidation","Ordinary and preferential shareholders are perpetual rivals"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between the output proceedings of Nigerians abroad and foreigners&nbsp; in Nigeria is known as;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Net export to abroad","Net import from abroad","Net income from abroad","Net income to abroad"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A stock variable is measured?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Over a period","At a point","Consistently","Intermittenly"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following is not true of price mechanism<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Equilibrium price is determined by forces  of demand and supply","Individual households and firms pursue personal interest","Producers and consumers are rational in decision making","Price control is prominent in the commodity and input markets"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economic system can be defined as an<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Arrangement specifying how production and consumption are controlled in a society.","Arrangement whereby goods are distributed in a society","Arrangement whereby human wants are satisfied in a society.","Arrangement specifying how productive resources are distributed in a society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are features of a free market economy except,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Private ownership of properties","Existence of competition","High level of profit maximization by private investors","Joint decision-making by the citizens in a society"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a capitalist society,&nbsp; production and consumption are regulated&nbsp; by the <\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand for the commodity","The government","Price system","Private individuals"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are advantages of socialism except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Equitable distribution of resources","Absence of exploitation","Equitable distribution of income","Promotion of high standard of living"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marginal product (MP) is best defined as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total product\/No of labour","Change in total product\/Change in variable factor","Total product\/Fixed factor","Average product\/No of labour"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT a limitation to division of labour and specialization&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The size of  the market","Availability of capital","Interdependence among the workers","The nature of the product"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic concepts of Economics are?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Choice, scarcity, resources and efficiency","Wants, scarcity, choice, scale of preference and opportunity cost","Wants, scarcity and choice","Wants, choice, scale of preference and opportunity cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics, human wants are usually described as?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Many","Insatiable","Limited","Numerous"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Basic economic problems of society include the following except:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["What to produce","How to produce","Where to produce","For whom to produce"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of money is measured in terms of price index as follows:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Price index = price in the previous year X 100%","Price index = price in the previous year \/ price in the current year X 100%","Price in the current year \/ velocity of circulation of money X 100%","Price index = price in the base year\/price in the current year X 100%"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marginal propensity&nbsp; to consumer (MPC) is calculated using one of the following formulae<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MPC= change in saving\/change in income","MPC = change in consumption\/change in income","MPC = 1\/1-MPC = 1\/MPS","MPC = Total saving\/Total income"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is TRUE of marginal cost ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a cost incurred by the firm on variable inputs","It is the cost of producing one extra unit of a commodity at any output level","It is the sum of the fixed cost and variable cost","It is referred to as overhead cost."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following items is NOT a variable cost<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cost of machine","Cost  of electricity","Salaries and wages","Cost of raw materials"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is NOT&nbsp; true of a market demand schedule ?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a  schedule of all consumers of a commodity in a market","It is the aggregate demand schedule of all customers of a commodity in a market","It is a table showing the different quantities of a commodity which a consumer would purchase at various prices","It is a table showing the composite demand schedule of all consumers of a commodity in a market"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Cross elasticity of demand can be measured using one of the formulae below . . .?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["% change  in quantity demanded \/ % change in sonsumers income","% change in quantity demanded \/ % change in price","% change in price of commodity \/ % change in quantity demand of  commodity x","% change in quantity demanded of commodity x \/ % change in price  of commodity y"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Price legislation can be defined as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["How price fluctuates in the market","How prices are controlled in the marker","How to avoid inflation","How the government fixes the prices of essential commodities"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Utility maximization occurs when one of the following conditions is attained&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mu =&#916;Tu\/ &#916;Q","mux\/px = muy\/py","px\/mux = py\/muy","mux\/muy= pxy\/muxy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the total cost of producing 600 units of a product is N21,000 and the average variable cost is N19, what is the average fixed cost?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N16","N35","N9,600","N21"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics, the pleasure, happiness, or satisfaction received from a product is called:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Rational outcome","Status fulfillment","Utility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A person should consume more of something when it's marginal:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Benefit exceeds its marginal cost","Cost exceeds its marginal benefit(s)","Cost equals its marginal benefit","Benefit is still positve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marcroeconomics can be described as the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Analysis of how consumer tries to spend income","Study of the large aggregates of the economy or the economy as as whole","Analysis of how firms attempt to maximize their profits","Study of how supply and demand determine prices in individual markets."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>When economists say that people act rationally in their self interest, they mean that individuals:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Look for and  pursue opportunities to increase their utility.","Generally disregard the nterests of others","Are mainly creatures of habit","Are unpredictable"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>As it relates to international trade, dumping:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is a form of price discrimination illegal under U.S. antitrust laws","Is the practice of selling goods inn a foreign market at less than cos","Constitutes a general case for permanent tariffs.","Is defined as selling  more goods than allowed by an import quota."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A nation's production possibilities curve is&nbsp; bowed out from the origin becaus<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Wants are virtually unlimited","The originator of the idea drew it this way and economists follow this modem convention","Resources are scarce.","Resources are not equally efficient in producing every good"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the production possibilities curve were a straight downsloping line, this would suggest that:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It  is possible to produce more of both products","resources are perfectly shiftable between the production of these two goods","Both products are equally capable of satisfying consumer wants","The two products have identical prices."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Productive efficiency refers to:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The use of the least-cost method of production","The production of the product-mix most wanted by society.","The full employment of all available resources","Production at some points  inside of the production possibilities curve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If depreciation exceeds gross investmentw:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The economy's stock of capital may be either growing or shrinking","The economy's stock of capital is growing","Net investment is zero","The economy's stock of capital is shrinking."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Assuming the total population is 100 million, the civilian labor force is 50 milllion, and 47 million workers are employed, the unemployment rate is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["3%","6%","7%","5.3%"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Unemployment involving a mismatch of the skills of unemployed workers and the skills required for available jobs is called:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Frictional unemployment","Structural unemployment","Cyclical unemployment","Compositional  unemployment"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The greater is the marginal propensity to consume, the :<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Smaller is the marginal propensity to save.","Higher is the interest rate","Lower is the average propensity to consume","Lower is  the price level"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Investment and saving are, respectively:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income and wealth","Stocks & flows","Injections and leakages","Lekages and injections"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The amount by which government expenditures exceed revenues during a particular year is the :<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Public debt","Budget deficit","Full employment","GDP gap"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of money varies _ _ _?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inversely with the price level","Directly with the volume of employment","Directly with the price level","Directly with the interest rate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If actual reserves in the banking system are 440,000, excess reserves are 4 10,000 and checkable depositss are 240,000, then the legal reserve requirement is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10%","12.5%","20%","5%"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The discount rate is the interest:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rate at which the Central Bank of Nigeria lends to the Nigerian Government","Yield on long-term government bonds","Rate at which commercial banks lend to the public","Rate at which the Central bank of Nigeria lend to commercial banks."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic formula for the price elasticity of demand coefficient is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Absolute decline in quantity demanded! absolute increase in price","Absolute decline in price\/absolute increase in quantity demanded","% change in price % change in quantity demanded","% change in quantity demanded % change in price"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a firm can sell 3,000 units of product A at $10 per unit and 5,000 at $8, then:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The price elasticity of demand is 0.44","A is a complementary good","The price elasticity of demand is 2.25","A is an inferior good."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Assume a household would consume N100 worth of goods and services per week if its weekly income were zero and would spend an additional p480 per week for each 600of additional income, the equation that summarizes this relationship is:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C=80 + 100Y","C=100 + 0.8Y","C= 100+80Y","C= 80+IY"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>For a bicycle company, an economist predicted that, other things being equal, a rise in consumer incomes will increase the demand&nbsp; for bicycles. This prediction is based on the assumption that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["There are many goods that are substitutes for bicycles","There are  many goods that are complementary to bicycles","There are few goods that are substitutes for bicycles","Bicycles are normal goods."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A demand curve which is parallel to the horizontal axis is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfectly inelastic","Perfectly elastic","Relatively inelastic","Relatively elastic."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Allocative efficiency occurs only at that output where:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal benefit exceeds marginal cost the by the greatest amount","Consumer  surplus exceeds producer surplus by the greatest amount","The areas of consumer and producer surplus are equal","The combined amounts of consumer surplus and producer surplus are maximized"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary problem of economics is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To obtain more equitable  distribution of money income","Production of a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital-intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factor of production."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A public corporation is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["an organ of local government","statutory quasi-autonomous public body","a specialised private sector enterprise","synonymous with privatisation of public bodies"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"}]